Guide to the Judith A. Fortney Papers, 1967-2004 RL.11195
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Judith A. Fortney Papers
1967-2004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
Fortney, J. A. (Judith A.), 1938-
RL.11195
4.5 Linear Feet
Judith A. Fortney is a public health scholar and researcher who received her PhD at Duke University and worked for Family Health International and the World Health Organization. This collection documents her professional activities.
Biographical / Historical
Judith A. Fortney has made significant contributions to research in the field of reproductive health, and has been actively involved in this research since 1974. She worked for Family Health International in North Carolina for 25 years where she was involved in research and writing surrounding maternal mortality and contraceptive epidemiology. She conducted the first RAMOS (Reproductive Age Mortality Survey) Study in Egypt and Indonesia in the early 1980s and has consulted for various U.N. agencies and NGOs. She also worked for the World Health Organization in Geneva where she developed strategies for their Safe Motherhood program, and was a long time member of the WHO contraceptive epidemiology committee and maternal mortality research committee. She has published widely in the field of reproductive health, including such topics as: contraceptive epidemiology, maternal mortality, and sexually transmitted infections.
She received a PhD in demography from Duke University, a master’s degree from the University of Wisconsin and a bachelor’s degree from the London School of Economics. She is an instructor at Columbia’s Mailman School of Public Health and an adjunct professor in the Department of Maternal and Child Health at the University of North Carolina.
Scope and Contents
The Judith A. Fortney papers document the professional activities of this pioneering women's health researcher. The materials in this collection include her writings and publications, project documentation, professional correspondence, subject files, photographs, and realia.
Arrangement
Arranged into three series: 1) Publications 2) Projects, Correspondence and Subject Files, and 3) Photographs and realia
Women in medicine; Abortion services -- Research -- Developing countries; Contraception -- Research -- Developing countries; Reproductive health -- Research -- Developing countries; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Fortney, J. A. (Judith A.), 1938-; Family Health International (Organization); World Health Organization. Reproductive Health and Research; Maternal Health and Safe Motherhood Programs
- Publications, 1967-2004
  - Early papers, 1967-1971 (Box 1)
  - Publications #1-10, 1970-1977 (Box 1)
  - Publications #11-20, 1978-1983 (Box 1)
  - Publications: Women's Magazine contraception article, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Publications #21-30, 1983-1986 (Box 1)
  - Reproductive Age Mortality Surveys (RAMOS), 1984-1989 (Box 1)
  - Publications #31-40, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Publications #41-50, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - Publications #51-60, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Publications #61-70, 1990-1993 (Box 2)
  - Political Constraints on Contraceptive Development in the US, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Publications, 1971-1996 (Box 2)
  - Safe Motherhood at the District Hospital: Project Report, 1995 (Box 2)
  - FHI Publications - Maternal Mortality and Morbidity in Sub-Saharan Africa, 1995 (Box 2)
  - FHI Publications - Reproductive Morbidity: A Conceptual Framework, 1995 (Box 2)
  - FHI Publications - The Base of the Iceberg, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Traditional Birth Attendants Bibliography, 1996 (Box 2)
  - In Her Lifetime: Female Morbidity and Mortality in Sub-Saharan Africa, 1996 (Box 2)
  - FHI Publications - Birth Kits: An Assessment, 1997 (Box 3)
  - FHI Publications - The Impact of TBA Training on the Health of Mothers and Newborns in Brong-Ahafo, Ghana, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Training of Traditional Birth Attendants: Issues & Controversies, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Publications #81-90, 1997-1998 (Box 3)
  - Publications, 2000-2004 (Box 3)
  - Typescripts of research papers, undated (Box 3)
- Projects, Correspondence and Subject Files, 1987-2000
  - Writings by others: UN Indicators for Monitoring the Availability and Use of Obstetric Services: A Revised Handbook, undated (Box 5)
  - Writings by others: WHO Maternal Health, Safe Motherhood Programme, undated (Box 5)
  - Reviews of papers, 1998 (Box 5)
  - Reviews of papers: Review of paper for Maternal & Child Health Journal, 1998 (Box 6)
  - Reviews of RFP: Health Services Research and Interventions in Safe Motherhood in Rural Balochistan, Pakistan, 1998 (Box 6)
  - Reviews of papers, 1999 (Box 6)
  - Writings by others: National Maternal Care Guidelines Nepal, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Writings by others: International Planned Parenthood Federation Directory of Contraceptives, 1981 (Box 5)
  - Writings by others: WHO: Global Strategy for Health for All by the Year 2000, 1981 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and subject files: International fertility research program hospital abortion record form, undated (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and subject files: UNC correspondence, 1998 (Box 5)
  - PATH, 1997-1999 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and subject files: Mothercare material, 1992-1999 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and subject files: misc. humorous material, 1981 (Box 5)
  - Projects: Effects of birth spacing on maternal mortality, 1993-1998 (Box 4)
  - Projects: Reproductive Morbidiy: A conceptual framework, 1995-1998 (Box 4)
  - Projects: Estimate of the MMR in 2 districts of the B-A region in Ghana, 1996-2000 (Box 4)
  - Projects: IUDs as longterm contraceptive methods, 1997-1999 (Box 4)
  - Projects: Role of frequent clinical contact in preventing FID, 1997-1999 (Box 4)
  - Projects: Maternal and neonatal health and nutrition program, 1998 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and subject files: FHI correspondence and ephemera, 1995-1998 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and subject files: FHI correspondence, 1999-2000 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and subject files: Jamaican's women's health study, 1999 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and subject files: Deborah Maine material, 1987-1995 (Box 4)
- Photographs and Realia, 1980s-1993 and undated
  - Cycle beads, undated (Box 7)
  - 2 photo albums documenting FHI work, 1980s (Box 7)
  - Vaginal contraceptive film in box, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Magnum condoms in box, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Manual vacuum aspirator with cannulas, undated (Box 7)